Guide to the National Lawyers Guild Records TAM.191
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
National Lawyers Guild Records
1921-2014, ongoing
1937-1990
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
National Lawyers Guild
Rabinowitz, Victor
Haney, Thomas M.
Tobol, Amy Ruth
Yoder, Tracy
TAM.191
311.25 Linear Feet in 316 boxes
8 CDs
11 websites in 11 archived websites.
208 audiocassette
The National Lawyers Guild (NLG) was founded in 1937 as an association of progressive lawyers and jurists who believed that lawyers had a major role to play in reconstructing legal values by emphasizing human rights over property rights. The Guild is the oldest and most extensive network of public interest and human rights activists working within the legal system. This collection includes early administrative records of the Guild, primarily those of its National Office and New York City Chapter, as well as materials describing legal and political activities of many of the Guild's chapters and committees. The collection also includes archived websites related to the NLG, captured since 2007. The bulk of the collection, however, is focused on the court case which revealed that the Guild had been the target of a forty-year covert Federal Bureau of Investigation campaign of surveillance, infiltration and intimidation (National Lawyers Guild v. Attorney General, 1977-1989). Through this legal action, the Guild successfully compelled the release of more than 400,000 pages of FBI documentation on the Guild and its members. This material, along with associated case files, is included in the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions with the exception of CD 4-6 located in box 311 of Part 2, Series XIX, which are restricted until December 2021.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact [repository contact information] with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by the Victor Rabinowitz on behalf of the National Lawyers Guild, 1999. Photographs in this collection were originally established as a separate collection and were received in three donations. Photographs were incorporated into this collection in 2014. Amy Ruth Tobol and Thomas Haney sent a donation of records related to their work with the National Lawyers Guild in 2014 In 2016, Tracy Yoder sent an additional donation of convention and publications records. In 2017, oral histories found in repository were added to the collection. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1997.027, 1997.046, NPA.2005.080, NPA. 2008.047, 2014.107, 2014.146, and 2015.015.
Websites were initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2007 as part of the Other Left Activism Web Archive. In 2012, crawling was stopped for https://nlginternational.org/, http://www.nationalimmigrationproject.org/, and https://www.nlg-npap.org/. In 2015, this website was migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In 2018, https://nlginternational.org/, http://www.nationalimmigrationproject.org/, and https://www.nlg-npap.org/ were re-added. The accession number associated with this accretion is 2019.107. In April 2020, the URL to http://www.nationalimmigrationproject.org/ redirected to https://nipnlg.org/ and was added to the web archive. The accession number associated with this website is 2020.033. In May 2020, http://nlg-laboremploy-comm.org/, https://nlgnyc.org/, and https://nlgmltf.org/ was added. The accession number associaed with these websites is 2020.047. In February 2021, Google documents and http://jailhouselaw.org/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2021.070. In December 2023, https://engage.nlg-npap.org/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2024.003. In 2025, https://www.nlgmic.org/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2025.066.
Appraisal
Photocopies and published materials including copies of National Lawyers Guild (NLG) periodicals, the Truth and Reconciliation Commission Final Report, and photocopies of documents from the NLG Records were removed from the 2015 accretion during accessioning.
Arrangement
The folders in Part 1 are arranged chronologically, except in series IV, XII, and XIV, which are arranged alphabetically. Arrangement of Part 2 varies, with most subseries in alphabetic sequence. Some of the subseries are arranged chronologically. Series I: Subseries B, which contains records of NLG national conventions, is an example of folders arranged by year. A number of subseries containing NLG v. AG court documents are also in date order. A few of the subseries, particularly those containing released government documents, reflect the order imposed by the FBI.
Part 1 is organized into 15 series and Part 2 is organized into 19 series. The first six contain material from the National Office and the New York City Chapter. The next seven involve the court case National Lawyers Guild v. Attorney General. Two series contain records from recent accretions, which are grouped roughly by creator or topic. The remaining series are grouped by format.
Part 1, Series I. Board of Directors (NYC Chapter) and Executive Board, 1937-1969
Part 1, Series II. Executive Officers, 1936-1968
Part 1, Series III. Statements, Resolutions, and Publicity Materials, 1937-1969
Part 1, Series IV. NLG Committees, 1937-1969
Part 1, Series V. Membership Records, 1938-1969
Part 1, Series VI. Chapter Records, 1937-1968
Part 1, Series VII. Convention Records, 1937-1968
Part 1, Series VIII. Publications, 1941-1967
Part 1, Series IX. Dinners, Events and Conferences, 1937-1978
Part 1, Series X. Political Issues, Including Government Investigations, 1942-1968
Part 1, Series XI. Legislation, 1936-1961
Part 1, Series XII. Cases: General Files, 1934-1967
Part 1, Series XIII. Correspondence, 1939-1969
Part 1, Series XIV. Subject Files, 1936-1976
Part 1, Series XV: Addendum, 1937-1968
Part 2, Series I. National Office Administrative and Organizational Records, 1931-2003
Part 2, Series II. National Office Programmatic Records, 1944-2001
Part 2, Series III. National Office Resource/Reference Material, 1949-1999
Part 2, Series IV. Publications and Press Materials, 1938-2004
Part 2, Series V. New York City Chapter Files - Administrative, 1937-2007
Part 2, Series VI. New York City Chapter Files - Programmatic, 1945-1985
Part 2, Series VII. NLG v. AG. Court Documents, Formal File, 1947-1990
Part 2, Series VIII. NLG v. AG. Discovery, 1921-1987
Part 2, Series IX. NLG v. AG. Reverse Discovery, 1937-1987
Part 2, Series X. NLG v. AG. Research, 1937-1988
Part 2, Series XI. NLG v. AG. Working Papers, 1936-1988
Part 2, Series XII. NLG v. AG. Administrative Material, 1937-1986
Part 2, Series XIII. NLG v. AG. Subject Files, 1930-1988
Part 2, Series XIV. 2014 Accretion, 1970s-1997
Part 2, Series XV. 2015 Accretion, 1960-2014
Part 2, Series XVI. Audiocassettes, 1981-1995
Part 2, Series XVII. Photographs, 1940s-1995
Part 2, Series XVIII. Archived Websites, 2007-ongoing
Part 2, Series XIX. Oral Histories
Historical Note
The Great Depression, with its social and political upheavals, also had its effects upon the nation's professional communities. Millions of workers -- native and foreign-born, black and white, male and female -- were being recruited to the ranks of organized labor. On the international scene, the rise of fascism in Europe was viewed with growing alarm on the left, and, by 1936, the first armed conflict again fascist forces was underway in Spain. The advent of the New Deal was also releasing forces for social progress and reform in every sector of the population. Little of this was reflected in the composition or activities of the American Bar Association and other professional legal organizations. Growing numbers of members of the profession were dissatisfied with the failure of their organizations to react to these dramatic social/political changes. This discontent found organizational expression in the formation of the National Lawyers Guild (NLG) in Feb 1937. Its avowed purposes would be to protect democratic institutions, individual rights, and advance "the legal well-being of the legal profession." (Weinberg and Fassler, Historical Sketch, p.1) Among the Guild's founding members were Morris Ernst, Jerome Frank, Senator Albert Wald, Frank Walsh, and the general counsels of both the American Federation of Labor and the Congress of Industrial Organizations. From its inception, the Guild welcomed into its ranks all members of the profession without regard to race, gender or ethnic identity; it was the first national legal professional association to do so.
The Guild's membership worked actively on a wide variety of issues. At the outset, it was instrumental in drafting, administering and litigating much progressive New Deal legislation. At the same time, it challenged all forms of discrimination and opposed limitations on the right of free speech. It also fought vigorously for the rights of workers to organize and bargain collectively. Many NLG members cooperated with the Congress of Industrial Organizations, and NLG work helped to shape the legal precedents that were later incorporated into labor law by the National Labor Relations Board.
The NLG's commitment to the right of freedom of expression became particularly meaningful with the establishment of a number of Congressional investigating committees, starting with the Dies Committee in the 1930s and continuing in the post-World War II period with the House Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC) and the McCarthy and McCarran Committees in the Senate. The Guild was steadfast in its opposition to the attempts of these committees to investigate the opinions and associations of private individuals. It also condemned the infringement of First Amendment rights by the federal loyalty program instituted by the Truman Administration. Similarly, it opposed the Smith Act prosecutions of the leaders of the Communist Party (later declared unconstitutional by the Supreme Court) and the requirement for registration of alleged "subversive" organizations under the Internal Security Act, also later declared unconstitutional. The Guild was vocal in its condemnation of abuses of individual rights by the F.B.I., for example, wiretapping, mail tampering, illegal searches and prying into citizens' beliefs and associations. It was also outspoken in seeking equal protection for the foreign born. During the McCarthy period Guild members defended many of the men and women who were subpoenaed by the Senate Internal Security Subcommittee and House Un-American Activities Committee.
Another important aspect of the Guild's work was its service in the communities. It established neighborhood law offices to serve people living in urban slums and provided advice to tenant councils, consumer groups and other community organizations. After its founding as a national organization in 1937, the Guild began establishing chapters in such cities as New York, Chicago, Philadelphia, Detroit, and San Francisco.
In 1944, the Guild's National Executive Board submitted a statement on the subject of punishment of war criminals and, as a result, was invited by the United States prosecutor, Justice Robert Jackson, to be official observers at the Nuremberg trials. Soon after, the U.S. State Department asked the Guild to act as an advocate/consultant to the U.S. delegation at the founding conference of the United Nations in San Francisco.
After World War II, the Guild was outspoken in its opposition to the nuclear arms race and urged a ban on all such weapons. It fought vigorously against the passage of the Taft-Hartley Act in 1947 which rolled back many of the protections the labor movement had secured a decade earlier under the Wagner Act.
From the beginning the Guild played an important role in the civil rights movement. In 1947, it convened a conference in order to respond to the lynching crisis in the South. As part of its commitment to civil liberties, it also furnished representation to the "Hollywood Ten" - writers and directors called to testify before and later jailed by the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC) for refusing to act as informers. The Guild also defended many veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade who had fought against fascism in Spain during the Spanish Civil War and were subjected to political persecution in later decades.
In the 1950s, HUAC labeled the Guild as a "Communist-front" organization and issued a publication entitled "The National Lawyers Guild: Legal Bulwark of the Communist Party." Attorney General Herbert Brownell asserted that the Guild was controlled by the Communist Party and attempted to label it a subversive organization dominated by a foreign power. He brought proceedings in 1953 which dragged on until 1958, at which time the Justice Department dropped its efforts because its evidence was deemed insufficient.
After a period of relative inactivity, the Guild responded quickly and energetically in support of the civil rights movement of the 1960s by establishing its Committee for Legal Assistance in 1962 to provide legal resources for those fighting racism and injustice in the South. It co-sponsored the first integrated bar conference in the South and opened the first office that provided legal representation to the civil rights movement. It also created the Committee to Aid Southern Lawyers and sent attorneys to the Southern states to represent civil rights activists.
During the late 1960s, the Guild worked closely with the peace movement defending many draft resisters and others who opposed the war in Vietnam. Student chapters of the NLG were formed in many cities. In the course of the decade the Guild was wracked by internal strains common to many old left organizations facing new challenges and a new generation of youthful activists. A rival progressive lawyers group, the Lawyers Constitutional Defense Committee, had emerged from the civil rights and anti-poverty movements and soon had chapters in most law schools. Eventually a cooperative relationship between the two organizations was worked out, and the Guild entered a period of renewed vitality under the presidency of prominent civil liberties attorney Victor Rabinowitz.
In the 1970s the NLG was actively involved in the struggles for affirmative action and women's and gay rights; organized defense teams for Native-American defendants from Wounded Knee; incarcerated people charged in connection with the Attica Prison uprising; and supported self-determination for Palestine and opposed apartheid in South Africa.
A new generation of legal activists during the 1980s organized support for the anti-nuclear movement and for groups opposing U. S. intervention in Central America and the NLG National Immigration Project began working on issues spurred by the need to represent Central American refugees and asylum activists fleeing Nicaragua and El Salvador. In 1989 the organization finally prevailed in its lawsuit against the FBI for carrying out illegal political surveillance.
Guild members mobilized in the 1990s in opposition to the Gulf War, defended the rights of Haitian refugees, opposed the blockade of Cuba and began to define a new civil rights agenda that included the right to employment, education, housing and health care.
Guild members continue into the twenty-first century using their experience and professional skills to support environmental and labor rights activists, fight for social justice, protect civil liberties and encourage respect for the Constitution and international law.
Sources:
Erlinder, Peter, History, National Lawyers Guild. http://nlg.org/aboutus/history.php, December 4, 2007.
Weinberg, Doron and Marty Fassler, A Historical Sketch of the National Lawyers Guild in American Politics, 1936-1968. National Lawyers Guild, n.d. Photocopy in Tamiment Library Vertical File: National Lawyers Guild.
Custodial History
The National Lawyers Guild records were acquired by the Tamiment Library in a series of accessions, from 1997 to 2007. Materials from the initial donation (Part I of this finding aid) were at one time housed at the Martin Luther King Center in Atlanta, Georgia. During the NLG v. Attorney General litigation, the materials were transferred back to the Guild and its legal representatives. The bulk of the collection was donated by Victor Rabinowitz who served briefly as Guild president and whose firm represented the Guild in National Lawyers Guild v. Attorney General.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Victor Rabinowitz Papers (TAM 123)
Rabinowitz, Boudin, Standard and Krinsky Records (TAM 287)
Jeanne Mirer Papers (TAM 383)
Related Materials Elsewhere
At the University of California at Berkeley are two collections: The National Lawyers Guild Records, 1937-1999, and the Meiklejohn Civil Liberties Institute Collections, both accessible via the following url: http://bancroft.berkeley.edu/collections/meiklejohn/findingaids.html
Scope and Contents
Part 1 of this collection documents the founding, development and day-to-day administration of the National Lawyers Guild from 1937 to 1969. Materials include the correspondence, agenda and minutes of the Board of Directors, the National Executive Board and the NYC Chapter Executive Board. Correspondence and other records also document in the work of the Executive Officers and their relations with NLG staff in several regions. The positions of the Guild on issues of the day are documented in resolutions, press releases, mailings and reports to members. Part I of the collections also includes records from NLG committees, including the Committee on Academic Freedom, the Civil Liberties and Civil Rights Committees, the Constitutional Liberties Committee, the Criminal Law Committee, the Labor Law Committee, the Committee on Professional Problems, the Committee on Social Legislation and several others. Membership records include correspondence, membership lists and a large number of resignation letters from members when the Guild was under attack from the Attorney General. The NYC Chapter is well represented in this collection, and the Chicago, Detroit, Los Angeles, Philadelphia and San Francisco chapters are also included. Materials pertaining to the Guild's conventions between 1937 and 1968 are included in Part I of this collection, including planning information, correspondence between board members, speeches made at conventions, and resolutions passed by the Guild. Records relating to other events, such as honoree dinners, theater parties and fundraising events are also included.
The Guild produced a number of publications, including the Lawyers Guild Review, the New York Guild Lawyer, Civil Liberties Docket, and the Guild Lawyer. The records for these publications are included in this collection. The Guild's response to Congressional hearings, subversive activities bills, HUAC operations, political attacks on Guild itself and political matters related to civil rights is also documented, as well as legislative initiatives on which the Guild acted, or upon which it took a position. Case and general files include background material on cases handled by the Guild, or in which it had a role, including Eisler v. the U.S., the Smith Act trials, the Rosenberg Case and others. Most of the cases are on the federal level, but there is also a substantial amount of material documenting cases at the state level. Subject files include a wide variety of topics of interest to the Guild. Of special note is material on the House Un-American Activities Committee. Included are clippings files maintained by the New York office. Correspondence files consist mostly of correspondence between the officers of various chapters and the national presidents. Additional correspondence and subject files can be found in the Addendum to Part 1.
Part 2 of this collection consists of subsequent donations, including National Office records, NYC Chapter records and files related to NLG v. Attorney General. Records of the National Executive Board and National Executive committee include minutes and related files, a variety of materials from most of the NLG's national conventions from 1973-2003 and a wide range of general administrative and organizational files. The activities of the NLG, including formal committees, legal work and general files reflecting projects, campaigns, endorsements, delegations, conferences, Guild positions and areas of activism and advocacy are documented, in particular through a relatively large section of the papers of Arthur Kinoy. The interested of the NLG National Office are also represented in legal cases of interest and various subject files. Also included are publications and related correspondence of the National Lawyers Guild, as well as non-NLG publications that were contained within the National Office files, and publicity materials such as clippings. The NYC Chapter is represented in this collection through administrative records such as minutes of the chapter's Executive Committee; materials generated by administrative committees; correspondence; files on chapter events; files relating to finances and membership; publications and resource material; as well as a wide variety of material describing the chapter's programmatic activities and advocacy.